A Guide to the Hideyo Noguchi papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA121
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hideyo Noguchi papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1904-1928 (also posthumous)
Rockefeller Archive Center
Noguchi, Hideyo
Flexner, Simon
FA121
4 Cubic Feet 7 boxes, 4 volumes, 1 package
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 450 N689
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, photographs obituary and biographical articles, newspaper items, reprints.
The papers consist of administrative correspondence, May 1900-May 1928; a large collection of photographs, collection of snapshots, photographs from Accra, photographs of diplomas, honors and medals; a large number of biographical articles and bibliography; a number of obituary articles and some historical articles; letters written from Accra relating to his research and conditions of work; correspondence with family representatives from Japan and with representatives of the Doctor Noguchi Memorial Association in Japan.
Arrangement
Chronologically within subject.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restriction
Biographical / Historical
Biography: Hideyo Noguchi (1876-1928) Japanese born bacteriologist who came to The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in 1904 and was successively Assistant, Associate Member and Member until his death in 1928. He worked closely with Simon Flexner. His first work was on the study of snake venoms. He then worked on collateral problems in immunology, syphilis and other forms of spirochetes and the etiological factors in Yellow Fever, Oroya Fever and trachoma. He served as bacteriologist of the Yellow Fever Commission sent by the International Health Board of The Rockefeller Foundation. He died at Accra, West Africa while on a project for the study of Yellow Fever.
Member of: American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists; Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine; Harvey Society; Society for Experimental Therapy and Pharmacology; Society for Clinical Serology and Haematology (President, Councilor); Gesellschaft für innere Medizin und Kinderheilkunde of Vienna; St Louis Medical Society of Syracuse (Honorary Member); Academy of Medicine of Suffolk Medical Society; Colorado State Medical Society; American Philosophical Society; Association of American Physicians; American Association for the Advancement of Science; Sociedade de Antonio Alzate, Mexico City; Mexican National Academy; Société de Biologie, Paris (Corresponding member); Société de Pathologie Exotique, Paris; Norske medizinake Selskab (Christiana); Société de Dermatologie et Venéreologie, Moscow; Accademia Medico-fisica Fiorentina, Florence; Sociedad Medica de Caracas (Venezuela); American Society for Experimental Pathology
Decorations
1913 Knight of the Royal Order of Isabella la Catolica (Spain); Knight of the Royal Order of Dannebrog (Denmark)
1914 Knight of the Order of the Pole Star (Sweden)
1915 Order of the Rising Sun (Japan); Emporor's Medal and Premium, Imperial Academy of Japan
1918 Hon. Senior Surgeon with rank of Colonel, Ecuadorean Army
1920 Hon. M.D. School of Medicine and Pharmacology, Yucatan
1918 Hon. Prof. University of Quayaquil; Hon. Prof. University of Quito
1920 Hon. Prof. University of Lima
1921 John Scott Medal, City of Philadelphia
1923 Elected Member of Imperial Academy of Japan
1924 Kober Medal, Association of American Physicians; Chevalier de la Légion d'Honneur, République de France; Medal from Elocution Soc. of Japan (one of 10 presented to 10 greatest Japanese); Medal from American Medical Association (Sc. Exhibit Yellow Fever, 1919); Medal from Asociacion Escuela de Medicina (Quayaquil); Medal from Asociacion de Empleados de Quayaquil and Los Centros de Trabajo (Quayaquil)
Honorary Degrees and Titles
1907 M.S. University of Pennsylvania
1911 - Titular Professor, University of Education of the Imperial Government of Japan
1914 Ph.D. Imperial University of Tokio
1921 Sc.D. Brown University; Sc.D. Yale University
1925 LL.D. Sorbonne, Paris (Doctor honoris causa)
Accra (Ghana); Japan; Rockefeller University; Noguchi, Hideyo; Flexner, Simon
- Biography and bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Copy of "Personal History." Memorial addresses by Theobald Smith and William H. Welch.
- Photographs, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes 1923 Visiting Commission of Medical Scientists (Japanese) and two supplied by Noguchi Memorial Association.
  Related Materials
  See also photo album, Box 6.
- 50 photographs of diplomas, degrees, honors and citation (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  Submitted (date?) by Robert G. Campbell of 1 East 66th St. New York City to P & S Medical Library. Glossy prints prepared at The Rockefeller Institute.
- Correspondence, May 1900 to October 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
  Only special items listed separately.
  - from H.N. to Simon Flexner from Chwang, China, 1900 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Details of experiments with plague and on preparations to leave for the United States (handwritten)
  - to Simon Flexner from Dr. Kitasato, Institut fuer, 1900 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Infektionskrankheiten, Tokyo introducing H.N. (handwritten)
  - Curriculum Vitae (handwritten), 1900 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - from H.N. to L. Emmett Holt accepting appointment (handwritten), 1904 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - from S. Solis Cohen to Simon Flexner (handwritten note), 1908 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - from H.N. to L. Emmett Holt (on reappointment) (handwritten), 1908 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Flexner-Noguchi-Dunham on joint study of lipoid preparations (handwritten), 17-19 August 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - from H.N. to Simon Flexner on paper for publication (handwritten), 14-16 June 1911 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Noguchi statement (handwritten) on value of luetin reaction, [1912]? (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - from Jerome D. Greene to New York county District Attorney in reply to accusations made by SPCC regarding luetin work. This is a draft and perhaps never sent or used., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - From Paul Ehrlich to H.N. (copies), February 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report on European trip, September-October 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From H.N. to Simon Flexner on hospitalization costs (handwritten), 1917 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From H.N. to E.B. Smith on laboratory needs while Noguchi on vacation (handwritten), 1919 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From Victor G. Heiser to H.N. confirming arrangements for International Health Board to meet cost of animals needed for production of Yellow Fever vaccine. (Typescript copy), 1920 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From Louis Otto Heiland for Board of Directors of City Trusts to H.N. awarding $800 for eminent scientific work. (copy), 1920 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Noguchi-Flexner on preparation of Rocky Mountain spotted fever vaccine, April-May 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - From College of Medicine, Bahia honoring Noguchi Includes translation and congratulatory letters from Wickliffe Rose and F.F. Russell, 1924 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Report on Yellow Fever work in Bahia
  - From E.B. Smith to dining room staff requesting special luncheon menu for Hideyo Noguchi, 1926 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding sterilization of glassware, May 1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence from Accra
  - letters and cables to Mary Noguchi (copies-5), 24 December 1927-7 April 1928 (Box 2)
  - correspondence and cables with Simon Flexner concerning details of work and illness. Letter of Jan. 1928 includes photos of two infected monkeys. (handwritten, typescript and copies-38), 29 October 1927-11 May 1928 (Box 2)
  - F.F. Russell to H. Noguchi 2 pages, 1928 February 1 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to E.B. Tilden (copy- 2 pages), 10-11 February 1928 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to E.B. Tilden (copy of cable), 1928 March 9 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to Ledingham (copy-3 pages), 1928 March 17 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to F.F. Russell (copy-4 pages), 1928 March 25 (Box 2)
  - Henry Beeuwkes to H. Noguchi (copy-2 pages), 1928 April 7 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to E.B. Tilden (copy of cable), 1928 April 13 (Box 2)
  - H.N. to F.F. Russell, 1928 April 21 (Box 2)
    2 page copy sent to S. Flexner including an 8 page handwritten letter from Noguchi to Russell protesting situation in regard to purchase of animals and reports on findings; includes Mar. 16 and Mar. 20 cables from Russell to Noguchi (copies)
  - E.B. Tilden to S. Flexner enclosing copies of letters from H. Noguchi of Apr. 8, and Mar. 14 and Mar. 20 letters from J. Bauer, 1928 May 21 (Box 2)
  - E.B. Tilden to S. Flexner on assistance for Mary Noguchi, 1928 May 22 (Box 2)
  - N. Paul Hudson to H. Beeuwkes enclosing brief experimental findings on tissues supplied by H. Noguchi, 1928 June 4 (Box 2)
  - R.C. Shannon to F.F. Russell listing specimens and materials (copy, 1928 June 13 (Box 2)
  - F.F. Russell to S. Flexner enclosing Hudson report (copy), 1928 July 12 (Box 2)
  - Henry R. Muller to S. Flexner recollection of laboratory situation in Accra. (Handwritten-3 pages), 1928 August 25 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, notes, cables, clinical reports, hospital records and laboratory reports on last illness and death in Accra of Hideyo Noguchi., 13 May 1928-August 1929 (Box 2)
  Biographical / Historical
  The death of Noguchi was followed in 8 days by the death of William A. Young.
  From Accra. Names of correspondents are: E. Morris Franklin (European Hospital); F.F. Russell, Director of International Health Division. Included are copies of correspondence from the American Consulate and British Colonial Office; copies of the autopsy report by N. Paul Hudson and Oskar Klotz; copies of diary, notes and letters from Henry Beeuwkes, Evelyn Tilden; A.F. Mahaffy; Helen Russell, pathologist; Agnes A. Young (mother) and Olive M. Young (wife) of Dr. William B. Young (picture included).
- Funeral Service in Accra, 1928 May 22 (Box 2)
- Accra photographs and negatives (Box 2)
- Gustav Eckstein, "Noguchi," New York, Harper, 1931, 1 volume (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Condolences from individuals, associations and embassies (Box 3)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically in each group.
- Funeral Service at The Rockefeller Institute, 1928 June 15 (Box 3)
  Includes lists of invited guests, seating arrangements, cards from floral tributes, glass color transparency of room arrangement at service. Typescript of addresses: Simon Flexner, J.D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dr. Fosdick
- Memorial Service at New York Academy of Medicine, 1928 December 20 (Box 3)
  Includes details of preparations and addresses
- Memorial meetings
  - Harbin, Manchuria, 1928 June 1 (Box 3)
  - Keijo, 1928 June 20 (Box 3)
  - Nippon Club, Tokyo, 1928 June 29 (Box 3)
  - Nippon Kogyo Club Bldg., Tokyo, 1928 June 29 (Box 3)
    Includes report of services and photograph
  - Report by G. Kawai on assorted memorial services in Japan, 1928 (Box 3)
  - At Japan Industrial Club in Marunouchi, 1928 June 29 (Box 3)
  - at Tokyo Dental College, 1928 July 3 (Box 3)
  - at Choshuji Temple, Sanjogata, Okinashima-Mura, 1928 July 8 (Box 3)
  - Emory Auditorium, Cinncinati, Ohio, 1928 November 18 (Box 3)
    Under the auspices of the Cinncinati Academy of Medicine; College of Medicine (Univ. of Cinn.); Public Health Federation
  - Handwritten remarks in handwriting of Simon Flexner -- dated May 15 but delivered by William H. Welch as a Memorial Address, 1929 (Box 3)
    see Box 1
  - Bronze memorial tablet unveiled, Faculty of Medicine, Bahia, Brazil, 2 April 1930 (Box 3)
- Woodlawn Cemetery (Box 3)
  Copy of deed to lots; map; correspondence about stone, tablet, planting. Trust agreement for upkeep.
- Correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 4)
  Deals mainly with details of Dr. Noguchi's estate and includes several handwritten letters from Mary Noguchi. Includes negotiations, lists and arrangements for items shipped to Japan and plans for a Memorial.
- Correspondence, 1932-1957 (Box 4)
  - Deals with requests for photographs and biographical materials. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Mr. S. Kobayahi (originals and translations) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, addresses and clippings on the opening of the Doctor Noguchi Memorial, 1939 May (Box 4)
  - Correspondence of 1955 indicates that the Noguchi medals were sent to Japan at that time (Box 4)
  - Correspondence between George Corner and Paul F. Clark on cause of Noguchi's death, 1957 (Box 4)
- Newspaper clippings, 1928 May 21-31, June 1 - December 31 (Box 4)
- Pamphlets and personal history, 1928 June 1 -1947 December 31
  - "Personal History" prepared by The Rockefeller Institute (duplicate in Box 1) (Box 4)
  - "Hideyo Noguchi; his life and work," published by Tokyo Dental College in August, 1928 (Box 4)
  - "Hideyo Noguchi," by Dr. Octavio Torres. Published in Bahia (duplicate in Box 5) (Box 4)
  - "The Dedication of the Doctor Noguchi Memorial Hall," Published 1939 by the Association (Box 4)
    duplicate in Box 5
- Noguchi Centennial, 5-12 November 1976 (Box 4)
  Working copy of book made up for presentation by Dr. and Mrs. Frederick Seitz at celebration of centennial of Dr. Noguchi's birth, in Japan.
- Hideyo Noguchi Medical history (Box 5)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Records from The Rockefeller Institute Hospital, Mt. Sinai Hospital, Accra
- Memorial items and information regarding reprint volumes (Box 5)
- Correspondence with Mr. Kobayashi carried on primarily through G. Kawai regarding a Memorial Association in honor of Dr. Noguchi., 1928 October - 1933 February 20 (Box 5)
  Includes details of memorabilia shipped to Japan; receipt of shipment; pictures of dedication of Memorial at birthplace (May 21, 1939).
- Dedication of Memorial Hall built adjacent to Noguchi's birthplace
  Pamphlets, pictures, mementos, rubbings sent to The Rockefeller Institute or brought by returning visitors.
  - "The Dedication of the Doctor Noguchi Memorial Hall," this pamphlet has been prepared by way of a report on the opening ceremony of the Doctor Noguchi Memorial Hall...dedicated May 21, 1939 (Box 5)
  - "Hideyo Noguchi," published by the Doctor Noguchi Memorial Association. Surugadai, Kanda, Tokyo 1940 (in English) (Box 5)
- Jerome D. Greene report on trip to Japan, 1929 (Box 5)
- Correspondence with family in Japan, May 1927-27 December 1931 (Box 5)
  Translation of one letter written by Noguchi to Sakae Kobayashi; others to John D. Rockefeller, Mary Noguchi and Simon Flexner. Some with attached Japanese originals.
- Published pamphlets, obituaries, memorial addresses
  - Simon Flexner
    - "Hideyo Noguchi," Scientific Monthly, 27(1928) 89-91, 2 copies (Box 5)
    - "Hideyo Noguchi," Smithsonian Report, 1929, 595-608 (Box 5)
    - "Hideyo Noguchi," Science, 69 (1929), 653-660 (Box 5)
  - Revue medicale et scientifique, 6(1928) (Box 5)
  - Metropolitan Nursing Service Newsletter, 5 July 1928 (Box 5)
  - Otavio Torres
    - "Hideyo Noguchi" Bahia. Maio de 1928...Nobre da faculdade de medicina, em homenagem ao sabio, 46 pages (Box 5)
  - Theobald Smith, William H. Welch
    - "Memorial Address" in "Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine," 5 (1929) 877-886 (Box 5)
    - "On the Trail of the Yellow Fever Germ," "American Review of Reviews," Apr. 1920, 386-392, April 1920 (Box 5)
  - "Sciencia Medica," 1 (1923) 282-283 (Box 5)
  - "JAMA," 90 (1928) 1727 (Box 5)
  - "Literary Digest," 1928 June 2 p.19, 2 June 1928 (Box 5)
  - "Science Newsletter," 13 (1928) 338 (Box 5)
  - "New York State Journal of Medicine," 1928 July 1, p.788, 1 July 1928 (Box 5)
  - "Nature," 1928 June 9 p.914, 9 June 1928 (Box 5)
  - "Lancet," 1928 June 2, p. 1144, 2 June 1928
  - "Pioneer Bacteriologist" "MD," 20 (1976) 143-150 (Box 5)
  - Some translations from Japanese newspapers and Russian Journal of Microbiology (Box 5)
- Photograph Album, 1915-1927 (Box 6)
  Presented to Simon Flexner as gift at Christmas by Evelyn Tilden and Dr. Muller.
- Collected Reprints, 1902-1929; 3 volumes (Box 6)
  v. 1 has bibliography
- Presented to Mrs. F. Seitz, on occasion of 1976 Centennial celebration, 1 volume (Box 6)
  Published by Noguchi Memorial Association.
- Photos, framed drawing and 2 diplomas, 1 package, oversize. (Package 1)
  - Etching portrait (profile) of Hideyo Noguchi by Emma Löwenstamm (Package 1)
    Numbered 83/150. Purchased by The Rockefeller Institute in 1958. Included is the correspondence concerned with the purchase.
  - Photographs of the etching, 2 photographs (Package 1)
  - Photograph of etching by Löwenstamm, Wien (Front view), 1913 (Package 1)
  - Photographs of bust by Konenkov (different views) (Package 1)
    General
    2 photographs.
  - Honorary diploma accompanying medal for Knight of the Royal Order of Isabella la Catolica (Spain), 1913 (Package 1)
  - Honorary diploma: Knight of the Royal Order of Dannebrog (Denmark), 1913 (Package 1)
- Plesset, Isabel R. Noguchi and his patrons. Assoc. Univ. Presses, 1980; 1 volume
- Hideyo Noguchi papers on microfilm, 2 reels, 16mm in cartridge (Box 6)
- "Hideyo Noguchi - The Centenary of His Birth," videocassette, 16 December 1976 (Box 7)
  Produced by NHK, LTD. In Japanese with some English interviews. Broadcast on December 16, 1976.
- Addition to the collection, March 1986
  Received March 1986 from National Archives.
  - Electrostat copies of selected records from the Department of State, 1913-1938; 16 pp.
    Decimal file relating to Noguchi.
- Addition to the collection, 30 January 1987
  Rec'd 30 January 1987. Delivered to RU Library by Mr. E. Mugdan on behalf of Dr. Klaus Emicke, Hamburg.
  - Portrait of H. Noguchi by Emma Löwenstam, oversize